Link, Eugene P.; Papers apap025
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Eugene P. Link Papers1907-1993
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Link, Eugene P., 1907-
apap025
7 cubic ft.
History Professor and activist for unionism, this collection contains correspondence and rsearch files on Harry F. Ward, American medical history, and other subjects.
Biographical Sketch
NOTE: The information found in this sketch comes from Eugene Link's resume (ca. 1984) which includes narrative annotations by his wife Beulah. The resume was updated upon the accession of the Link Papers from 1991-1993. Biographical information about Link can also be found in Ann Evory, ed., Contemporary Authors: A Bio-Bibliographical Guide to Current Authors and Their Works, vols. 37-40, 1st revision (Detroit, Michigan: Gale Research Co., 1979), 333 and Jaques Cattell Press, Directory of American Scholars, 8th ed., vol. I (New York & London: R.R. Bowker Co., 1982), 455.
Eugene Perry Link was a son of the American Midwest. Born in Paris, Illinois on September 4, 1907, Link spent most of his early life in Emporia, Kansas, where he attended high school. His parents were Nathaniel (a pharmacist of some renown) and Lidabelle Link. As the middle child of the Link family (he had an older brother, Wendell, and a younger sister, Lidabelle), young Eugene distinguished himself early on through academics and through his oratory skills, winning the Kansas State Oratorical Contest four times during his high school and college years.
In the midst of the Great Depression, Link resolved to pursue an academic career. He graduated with the B.A. degree from the College of Emporia in 1929; three years of graduate study at the University of Chicago followed (1929-1931). Forced to leave Chicago because of finances, Link won an honors scholarship to Union Theological Seminary in 1931. Link's decision to attend a religious seminary is instructive of his later career. From the early 1930s onward, his academic scholarship would be consistently informed by Christian ethics and social justice. No person (other than his wife and collaborator, Beulah, whom he married in 1938) would make a greater impression on Link than Dr. Harry F. Ward, professor of ethics at Union Seminary and co-founder of the American Civil Liberties Union. In many ways, Link's mature career was an effort to expand upon and apply the earlier work of his mentor, Ward.
Although he was ordained to the ministry of the Congregational Church in 1933, from the mid-1930s onward, Link's professional arena was predominantly the classroom. He held a succession of academic positions over four decades: Instructor of History, Mt. Hermon School, Mt. Hermon, Massachusetts (1933-1937); Assistant Professor of Social Science, Limestone College, Gaffney, S.C.(1938-1940); Professor and Chair of Sociology, State Women's College, Rock Hill, S.C. (1942-1944); Professor of Social Science, State Teachers College, Montclair, N.J. (1944-1946); Professor and Chair of Sociology, University of Denver, Denver, Colorado (1946-1950); Professor and Divisional Chair of Social Science, State University of New York, New Paltz (1950-1963); and Research Professor of American Social History, State University of New York, Plattsburgh (1963-1977; emeritus after 1977). Largely through part-time attendance in the late 1930s, Link obtained his Ph.D. in social history from Columbia University in 1941.
As Link matured professionally, he increasingly concentrated on those groups that have tended to suffer from the abuses of the capitalist system: laborers, women, minorities, and Third World nations. This emphasis can be seen as a natural extension of the "Social Gospel" doctrine formulated by Washington Gladden, Walter Rauschenbusch, Harry F. Ward, and others. As a teacher at Plattsburgh, Link was among the first to champion an expanded curriculum in the social sciences that examined those who were traditionally ignored in social history.
Link's greater renown comes from the degree to which he has been able to translate his concern for social justice into action. He has traveled abroad extensively. He served as a Fulbright Lecturer in India two different times (1954 and 1960) and strongly urged the United States government to establish diplomatic relations with the Peoples Republic of China in the 1970s. The clearest example of Link's penchant for action rather than theory, however, has been his long association with the American Federation of Teachers (since 1935) and the United University Professions. In the 1970s, Link held the important offices of Vice President in the New York State University Federation of Teachers and served as leader for Membership Development for the United University Professions. He was also instrumental in the creation of the Committee of Active Retired Members (CO-ARM) of the UUP. His experience and counsel have been sought repeatedly by union organizers from campuses around the nation.
The varied interests of Link can be seen in his numerous publications and correspondence. His major books are The Democratic-Republican Societies (Columbia University Press, 1942); Victories in the Villages (National Council on Educational Research and Training, 1964); The College of Emporia: Retrospection and Appreciation (Vermont Villanti Press, 1982); Labor-Religion Prophet: The Times and Life of Harry F. Ward (Westview Press, 1984); The Humanitarian Tradition in American Medicine: The Social Ideas of Physicians (Academy of Independent Scholars, 1990); and The T.B.'s Progress: Norman Bethune As Artist (Plattsburgh State University, 1991). In addition, Link has produced dozens of scholarly articles, book reviews, and unpublished prose essays dealing with American social history, marriage and family relations, the medical profession, and labor unions.
Link carried on a wide array of correspondence with colleagues and students. Of special interest are letters to and from George Angell, Herbert Aptheker, Lee Ball, Cyril Bibby, Merle Curti, Buell Gallagher, Arnold Johnson, and Corliss Lamont. Most of these letters are preserved in the Eugene P. Link Papers.
Officially retired from SUNY, Plattsburgh since 1977, Link remained very active as an author and union activist. His three children, Martha (Mrs. Charles Casey), Perry Jr., and Bruce all followed their father into professions in academia. Dr. Link died on April 26, 2006.
Scope and Contents
The papers of Eugene P. Link contain autobiographical materials, memorabilia, family and professional correspondence with colleagues and publishers, lecture notes, published and unpublished manuscripts, and offprints of colleagues articles related to Link's career as a teacher, author, social historian, labor activist, and Christian minister. In particular the collection reflects Link's life-long commitment to social and economic justice, free speech, and religious tolerance in a pluralistic society. Included in the Link Papers are the papers of his wife and collaborator, Beulah Link, Harry Ward, his teacher and mentor at Union Theological Seminary and the records of the Reilgious Freedom Committee (1954-1964.).
Prominent correspondents includes academicians and social activists Herbert Aptheker (long time director of the American Institute of Marxist Studies); Lee Ball (director of the Methodist Federation of Social Action, 1960-73); Cyril Bibby (noted British scholar on the Huxley family and Principal of Kingston upon Hull College of Education, 1959-76); Merle Curti (professor and professor emeritus of American history at the University of Wisconsin--Madison, 1947-1996); Buell Gallagher (professor of Christian ethics, champion of academic freedom and civil rights, and president of the City College of New York, 1952-69); Arnold Johnson (national legislative director of the Communist Party, U.S.A. for nearly forty years); and Corliss Lamont (noted political, philosophical, and economic critic of capitalism).
Other series of interest to researchers include Dr. Link's labor activities (1966-1992) and teaching career (1933-77, 1985). Unfortunately, the early materials relating to Dr. Link's participation in the American Federation of Teachers (1935-1965) and the founding of the United University Professions, Inc. are not included in this collection. The teaching career materials include institutional correspondence and lecture notes on social history courses taught at the State University Colleges at New Paltz and Plattsburgh, and Hull House, England.
Dr. Link's publications include over forty articles, primarily in the area of social history and the social ethic of Canadian and American physicians including the Barton brothers, Norman Bethune, Elizabeth Blackwell, Harvey Cushing, Abraham and Mary Jacobi, Johnathan Knight, and the Mayo family. A major Link publication is Labor-Religion Prophet: The Time and Life of Harry F. Ward (Boulder, CO; Westview Press, 1984.).
Link's extensive research files on Ward include three of Ward's unpublished manuscripts. Ward (1873-1966) was an ordained minister in the Methodist Episcopal Church; professor of Christian ethics at Union Theological Seminary from 1918-41 (and emeritus after 1941 until his death in 1966); a founder of the Methodist Federation of Social Service in 1907; and chair of the American Civil Liberties Union from 1920-40 and founder of the Religious Freedom Committee.
The Link Papers contain the records of the Religious Freedom Committee for the years, 1954-1964, including minutes of its Administrative Committee, financial and membership records, its newsletter "Religious Freedom News", and occasional publications. The Religious Freedom Committee was an interfaith, interracial group founded in New York City to work for the free exercise of religion under the First Amendment.
Arrangement of the Collection
Divided into 8 topical series, some with subseries.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by Eugene P. Link from April 1991 - March 4, 1993. Additional accessions were added in 2002 and 2003.
Related Materials
Additional labor collections in the Department are available at the online Labor subject guide at http://library.albany.edu/speccoll/labor.htm and education collections are available at the online Education subject guide at http://library.albany.edu/speccoll/education.htm.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Tuberculosis -- Patients -- New York (State) -- Saranac Lake -- Biography.; Physicians as artists.; Education; Labor; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Bethune, Norman.; Link, Eugene P., 1907- -- Autographs.
- Autobiographical and Family Correspondence, 1907-1993; 1; 1.2 cubic ft.
  Scope and Contents
  This first series is further divided into two sub-series: (1) autobiographical and biographical; and (2) family correspondence.
  The autobiographical and biographical materials span the entire length of Eugene Link's life: grade school materials; his Emporia, Kansas, high school yearbook and diploma; papers from his undergraduate college (the College of Emporia) and various graduate institutions (the University of Chicago, Union Theological Seminary, and Columbia University); and alumni papers. Some of the materials in this subseries relate to Link's father, Nathaniel, a pharmacist in Emporia, who invented a well-known medicinal cream known as GIMP.
  The papers of Link's wife, Beulah (they were married in 1938), also figure prominently in this subseries. Possessing a particular interest in mental retardation, Mrs. Link taught for thirty-one years at the elementary, high school, and college levels. Several of her articles were published over the years in various educational journals. Mrs. Link was her husband's partner in every sense of the word: as a union supporter, a counselor, an editor of Eugene Link's writings, and a supportive critic of his ideas and teachings.
  The second division of series one deals with a voluminous family correspondence. A highly educated family, the Links saw all three of their children proceed to graduate school and careers in higher education. Martha Link Casey, possesses a doctorate in chemistry and has, since the mid-1970s, served on the administrative staff of the University of Wisconsin at Madison. Their elder son, Eugene Perry, Jr., is a professor of East Asian studies at Princeton University. Younger son, Bruce, possesses a doctorate in psychiatry from Columbia University. The correspondence of the Link children sheds significant light upon the personal life of Dr. and Mrs. Link.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Subseries 1: Autobiographical and Biographical, 1907-1993; 1.1
    - Appointment Books, 1974-1992 (Box 1 (1-Autobiographical and Family Correspondence), Folder 1)
    - Baby Book, 1907-1909 (Box 1 (1-Autobiographical and Family Correspondence), Folder 2)
    - College of Emporia [with diploma], 1925-1929 (Box 1 (1-Autobiographical and Family Correspondence), Folder 3)
    - College of Emporia Alumni Correspondence, 1969-1989; 2 folders (Box 1 (1-Autobiographical and Family Correspondence), Folder 4-5)
    - Columbia University, New York City, 1937-1956; 2 folders (Box 1 (1-Autobiographical and Family Correspondence), Folder 6-7)
    - Columbia University, Notebooks, Ph.D. Studies, 1936-1940 (Box 1 (1-Autobiographical and Family Correspondence), Folder 8)
    - Community Activities, Plattsburgh, New York, 1964-1993 (Box 1 (1-Autobiographical and Family Correspondence), Folder 9)
    - English I Composition Book, 1922 (Box 1 (1-Autobiographical and Family Correspondence), Folder 10)
    - Genealogical Materials on the Link Family, Undated (Box 1 (1-Autobiographical and Family Correspondence), Folder 11)
    - High School Yearbook, Emporia [Kansas] High School, 1925 (Box 1 (1-Autobiographical and Family Correspondence), Folder 12)
    - Link, Beulah, Personal Papers [with photos], 1930s-1992 (Box 1 (1-Autobiographical and Family Correspondence), Folder 13)
    - Link, Beulah M., Scholarship Fund, Midland College, Fremont, Nebraska, 1986-1988 (Box 1 (1-Autobiographical and Family Correspondence), Folder 14)
    - Link, Nathaniel [Link's father], Formulas for His Drug Company, Undated (Box 1 (1-Autobiographical and Family Correspondence), Folder 15)
    - Management of the Link House, Plattsburgh, New York, 1964-1992 (Box 1 (1-Autobiographical and Family Correspondence), Folder 16)
    - "A Minute for Wendell Athey Link, My Brother", 1990s (Box 1 (1-Autobiographical and Family Correspondence), Folder 17)
    - Notebook, ca. 1920 (Box 1 (1-Autobiographical and Family Correspondence), Folder 18)
    - Personal Papers before 1925 (incl. photos), Undated (Box 1 (1-Autobiographical and Family Correspondence), Folder 19)
    - Placement, Link's Requests For, 1941-1953 (Box 1 (1-Autobiographical and Family Correspondence), Folder 20)
    - Reference, Letters of in Behalf of Link, 1941-1979 (Box 1 (1-Autobiographical and Family Correspondence), Folder 21)
    - Resume and Photos of Eugene Link, Undated (Box 1 (1-Autobiographical and Family Correspondence), Folder 22)
    - Retirement From Plattsburgh State University, Eugene Link, 1977 (Box 1 (1-Autobiographical and Family Correspondence), Folder 23)
    - Trusteeship, Hope College, Michigan, 1958; 1963-1965 (Box 1 (1-Autobiographical and Family Correspondence), Folder 24)
    - Union Theological Seminary [with materials on Link's ordination to the ministry], 1931-1935 (Box 1 (1-Autobiographical and Family Correspondence), Folder 25)
    - University of Chicago, 1929-1931 (Box 1 (1-Autobiographical and Family Correspondence), Folder 26)
    - Wedding of Eugene and Beulah Link, 1938 (Box 1 (1-Autobiographical and Family Correspondence), Folder 27)
  - Subseries 2: Family Correspondence, 1918-1992; 1.2
    - Casey, Martha Link [Link's daughter], 1950-1992; 3 folders (Box 1 (1-Autobiographical and Family Correspondence), Folder 28-30)
    - Link, Arthur S. [distant relative; professor at Princeton], 1961-1989 (Box 1 (1-Autobiographical and Family Correspondence), Folder 31)
    - Link, Beulah to Eugene Link, 1937-1992 (Box 1 (1-Autobiographical and Family Correspondence), Folder 32)
    - Link, Bruce [Link's younger son], 1958-1992; 2 folders (Box 1 (1-Autobiographical and Family Correspondence), Folder 33-34)
    - Link, Eugene to his Family, 1939-1964 (Box 1 (1-Autobiographical and Family Correspondence), Folder 35)
    - Link, Mr. and Mrs. Nathaniel, 1918-early 1940s (Box 1 (1-Autobiographical and Family Correspondence), Folder 36)
    - Link, Perry [Link's older son], 1954-1989; 2 folders (Box 2 (1-Autobiographical and Family Correspondence), Folder 1-2)
    - Link, Wendell Senior [Link's brother] and Junior and Families, 1947-1992 (Box 2 (1-Autobiographical and Family Correspondence), Folder 3)
    - Link Grandchildren ["Sasha", J. Casey, Monica and Nathan Link], 1977-1992; Undated (Box 2 (1-Autobiographical and Family Correspondence), Folder 4)
    - Meyer Family Correspondence [Beulah Link's family], late 1930s-1967 (Box 2 (1-Autobiographical and Family Correspondence), Folder 5)
    - Schwegler, Lidabelle Link [Link's, sister], 1940-1979 (Box 2 (1-Autobiographical and Family Correspondence), Folder 6)
    - Rockwell Kent Painting, "Sacco and Vanzetti", Correspondence and Photographs, 1994-2000 (Box 7 (1-Autobiographical and Family Correspondence), Folder 13)
- Professional Correspondence, 1933-1993; 2; 1 cubic foot
  Fully one-seventh of the Link Papers are composed of a highly eclectic professional correspondence with many significant academicians and social activists from the political left. Sensitive to the abuses of capitalism, tempered by the Great Depression and New Deal politics of Franklin Roosevelt, Link and his associates were firmly committed to social and economic justice for all, absolute free speech, and religious tolerance in a pluralistic society. Link's professional correspondents include: Herbert Aptheker (long time director of the American Institute of Marxist Studies); Lee Ball (director of the Methodist Federation of Social Action, 1960-73); Cyril Bibby (noted British scholar on the Huxley family and Principal of Kingston upon Hull College of Education, 1959-76); Merle Curti (professor and professor emeritus of American history at the University of Wisconsin--Madison, 1947-1996) (approximately 200 letters); Buell Gallagher (professor of Christian ethics, champion of academic freedom and civil rights, and president of the City College of New York, 1952-69); Arnold Johnson (national legislative director of the Communist Party, U.S.A. for nearly forty years); and Corliss Lamont (noted political, philosophical, and economic critic of capitalism).
  The professional correspondence also contains letters from Link's academic colleagues in Britain (he served as a visiting professor at Hull in 1975) and India (mostly through the faculty of Annamalai University where Link served as a Fulbright Lecturer in the 1950s), old college alumni (Dwight Leonard and David L. Miller) and many letters from legislators (U.S. Representatives, U.S. Senators and Governors from New York State).
  The correspondence illustrates an evolution of Link's views toward an increasingly left-wing stance in the 1970s and 1980s. This evolution is underscored by Link's financial contributions to the Communist Party, U.S.A.
  - Academy of Independent Scholars, 1982-1986 (Box 2 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 7)
  - American Civil Liberties Union and Methodist Federation for Social Action, 1973-1987 (Box 2 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 8)
  - Appreciation, Expression Of By Former Students, ca. 1950-1984 (Box 2 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 9)
  - Appreciation/Recognition Letters/Awards to Link, 1938-1991 (Box 2 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 10)
  - Aptheker, Herbert, 1974-1984 (Box 2 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 11)
  - Ball, Lee, 1967-1984 (Box 2 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 12)
  - Bibby, Cyril, 1962-1973 (Box 2 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 13)
  - Books Donated to Various Universities [Cornell, Vermont, SUNY-Albany] by Link, 1984-1985; 1987; 1992 (Box 2 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 14)
  - Britain, Colleagues From [excepting Hull Lectureship], 1962-1974; 1976-1992 (Box 2 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 15)
  - China, Link's Visit To [1983-84], 1983-1990 (Box 2 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 16)
  - China Trips, Presentations, 1977-1984 (Box 2 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 17)
  - Colvin, Harold, 1984-1995; Undated (Box 2 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 18)
  - Communist Party of the USA [with letters from Arnold Johnson and Gus Hall, receipts of financial contributions, and photos], 1970s-1980s (Box 2 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 19)
  - Curti, Merle, Correspondence, 1939-1973 (Box 2 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 20)
  - Curti, Merle, Correspondence and Photographs, 1974-1992 (Box 2 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 21)
  - Curti, Merle, Correspondence From and Regarding; Memorial Service, Photographs, 1992-1996 (Box 2 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 22)
  - Curti, Merle, Eightieth Birthday Festschrift, 1973-1977 (Box 2 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 23)
  - Dombrowski, Jim, 1974-1980 (Box 2 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 24)
  - Gallagher, Buell, 1934-1962 (Box 2 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 25)
  - Gorton, John and Sally [formerly Mrs. Rockwell Kent], 1942-1991 (Box 2 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 26)
  - Horton, Myles [with information on the Highlander School], 1974-1977 (Box 2 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 27)
  - Hu, C. T., 1962-1985 (Box 2 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 28)
  - Hull Lectureship, 1974-1975 (Box 2 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 29)
  - India, Colleagues From, 1960-1976 (Box 2 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 30)
  - Jones, Dan Burne, 1984-1986 (Box 2 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 31)
  - Kent-Delord Collection, 1965-1983 (Box 2 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 32)
  - Lake Champlain Pollution, 1970-1987 (Box 2 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 33)
  - Lamont, Corliss, 1984-1989 (Box 2 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 34)
  - Legislators on Various Matters [many addressed to Beulah Link], 1965-1992 (Box 2 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 35)
  - Leonard, Dwight, 1978-1990 (Box 2 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 36)
  - Manealoff, Dorothy [wife of financial supporter of Harry F. Ward], 1973-1983 (Box 2 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 37)
  - Marriage and the Family, 1952-1953 (Box 2 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 38)
  - Menon, Kamala, [Wife of T.K.N. Menon], 1964-1967 (Box 2 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 39)
  - Miller, David L. [college alumnus and Univ. of Texas professor of philosophy], 1972-1978 (Box 2 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 40)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence to Beulah Link, 1940-1993 (Box 2 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 41)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence to Eugene Link, 1931-1973 (Box 2 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 42)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence to Eugene Link, 1974-1994 (Box 3 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 1)
  - Mohonk Mountain House, 1971-1987 (Box 3 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 2)
  - Okong'o, Peter [brother of Tom Mboya; with photo], 1960-1970 (Box 3 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 3)
  - Preservation and Conversation Issues [i.e. Adirondack Park], 1974-1987 (Box 3 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 4)
  - Summer Community of Scholars Program, SUNY, Plattsburgh, 1967-1971; 2 folders (Box 3 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 5-6)
    Including photos.